[Music] so i'm reading some suitors um
so i'm reading some suitors um
in a
chapter called summer cheetah the
peaceful mind
in there and good or any kind
this is a small one first
it says uh mandicans
because i will teach you the level of a
bad of the bad person and the level of a
good person
what is the level of a bad person the
bad person is ungrateful and thankless
for the wicked only know how to be
ungrateful and thankless
and it is totally the level of a bad
person to be ungrateful and thankless
the good person is grateful and thankful
for the virtuous only know how to be
grateful and thankful
the good only know how to be
grateful
but how how what is gratitude you know
how is one truly
uh grateful but being virtuous
so that's that's the important bit to
recognize gratitude is no matter of choice or i
gratitude is no matter of choice or i
shall be grateful
or i shall not be grateful because often
people think oh you should be great
makes yourself grateful
as a suitor says if you're virtuous
gratefulness is the result of it whether
you want it or not
that's why you can only know how to only
knows how to be grateful a virtuous
person he really knows how to be
virtuous because of the virtue
because of the virtue
he can only be grateful he cannot be
ungrateful because it's it's grateful and state of
because it's it's grateful and state of
mind
you can say all you want i really
appreciate that thank you very much i'm
so grateful but not really have that
state of mind
but that state of mind of gratefulness
is the result of virtue
and consequently state of mind of
non-gratefulness is the result of lack
of virtue by being
non-virtuous you cannot appreciate
you don't care about what others the
gifts of others well you might get on
the superficial level fundamentally you
are not in that frame of mind
because that frame of mind can only be
developed through virtue
so it's
it's not a matter of choice
to be grateful or not even if you never
say you're grateful
and never say you appreciate anything if
you're virtuous you are grateful you
appreciate everything
but you will make it yourself you are
being because you are being careful well
exactly yeah
yeah that's why you purchased you're
careful you consider it
you consider things so
and that's already the
type of outlook
that is kind of that leads to
gratefulness
so when people want sometimes
make a practice of how they say
conscious gratitude or something
well you just have to be virtuous
you just have to be virtuous
and you'll be consciously grateful
but if you make a practice of conscious
gratitude i don't know like fabricating
and emulating and doing the great
gratitude and gratefulness and
constantly dwelling on it but you're not
virtuous that's some gratefulness
so it's not yeah it's not what you say
it's not what you say
what state of mind you have overall
of course
so so a person gets a
college fund
and they
they say thank you
thank you dad for paying for my college
i really appreciate it but all he does
is
party doesn't study he doesn't well
exactly so he might like and that's
another thing like i think people would
often genuinely genuinely
uh conflate
happiness being pleased with
gratefulness oh you know you you made my wish come
oh you know you you made my wish come
true i'm so grateful no i'm really like
i'm just happy
because i got what i want
it doesn't necessarily mean you're in a
grateful state of mind
if you were virtuous then you would be
here because you wouldn't not be you
would not be able to be in any other
state of mind that's what the suit says
um
so yes exactly if you were grateful then
the value
of that which made you happy will not be
lost obscured forgotten about dismissed
disrespected naturally
naturally
naturally because through gratefulness
oh you value it i'm so grateful i
finally got what i want which is the
college fund so i'll take it seriously
and it will be effortless because you're
in a grateful state of mind
but yes if you dismiss it then don't
study and don't don't act
uh
towards it don't make the most of it
means oh yeah you were never grateful
you were just happy you got what you
want enjoy the ideas of it but then
enjoy the ideas of it but then
practically you're doing the opposite
things so again it comes down to the action
so again it comes down to the action
grateful
comes from the virtuous behavior
so if you act virtuously you practice
sensitive strain and guard other sensors
you will be grateful even for a little
thing because the value of it will not be
because the value of it will not be
obscured the value of it will not be
second put second and you put yourself
first and your animal needs first or
whatever else
they will all be maintained in the right
order so the grave only this will remain
so there's that
uh
and this the second suit that follows
this one
is the
because i say that these two people
cannot easily be repaid
what to mother and father
you would not have done enough to repay
your mother and father even if you were
to carry your mother around on one
shoulder and your father on the other
and if you live like this for a hundred
years and if you were anoint massage
bathe bathe them and even if they were to
bathe them and even if they were to
defecate and urinate right there
even if you were to establish your
mother and father as supreme
rulers of this great earth
bounding in seven treasures you would
still not have done enough to repay them
why is that
parents are very helpful to their
children they raise them nurture them
and show them the world
but you have done enough more than
enough we to repay them if you encourage
settle and ground
unfaithful parents in faith
unethical parents in ethical conduct
stingy parents in generosity or ignorant
parents and wisdom
and the common thread to all of that is
basically it's it's that
bigger perspective so it's not just
limit like
it's not just limited to this
life that's why it says like even if you
would establish them in the supreme
rulers even if you give them everything
in this world and make them the rulers
of this world
with all the seven treasures of this
world that's not enough because it's
only this world
but if you establish them in generosity
that pertains now to
future rebirths in ethical conduct that
pertains in future rivers in in right
view that pertains to future rivers or
you will have very modern enough because
you'll be paid not just for this life
but for a few because they would have
they would have missed out on that
because unethical person
will not benefit in the lives to come
because of the lacking lapping of ethics
and same with with virtue and others so
if you change that for them oh yeah you
repay them now for eons to come because
you establish them in generosity they
will pertain the results that will
pertain for a long time so yeah
you repay them
yeah you say okay so you can set them up
with a
a good lifestyle yeah with all the but
it's kind of limited yes it stays just
here that's it and from that point of
view yeah even if you give them
everything in the world
technically you don't kind of can't
repay them because they gave you life
but if you but if you give them more
than this not just this world but all
the next lives yeah in that way you gave
them future lives
of a better kind no not people anymore
and so on if you gave them future lives
basically fixing their lack of virtue
fixing their lack of faith
making them behave properly
because i was as i was also thinking
about that how to pay your parents
for doing what they've done but all
parents are the yeah of course
are great individuals yeah and
so
but they still did yeah well see that
that's how you pay them so even even
repaying your own parents even the debt
to your parents none of that needs to be
personal none of that needs to be on the level of
none of that needs to be on the level of
attachment like yeah but it's my parents
you know i must emotionally get involved
with with that relationship because i
owe them no no no that's your
willingness speaking
i must forsake my my training in virtue
and everything else because i need to
help my parents no that's your
worldliness and lack of right to you
speaking
it can stay impersonal and you can focus
on basically teaching them getting
through to them
because you know them because they are
your parents
uh
and establish them in proper behavior in
faith in virtue
and they do that well you gave them a
chance if they don't do it well you gave
them a chance
you can't do it for them you can't force
them so yes don't dismiss it like oh i don't
so yes don't dismiss it like oh i don't
care no you do actually
owe them they gave you life they
they the suitor says nurture you made
everything else
possible so so you owe them but that does not
so so you owe them but that does not
mean this kind of oh i must
like that whole
relationship it must always stay on the
level of attachment and this emotional
stickiness and stuff like that it's not
at all
there also
from the samsara point of view
random individuals passing through that
you know collided with and whatever else
and they'll carry on their own way
beings are owners of their own actions
and that's the direction they'll be
heading no matter how many sons and
daughters you had and how much they're
helping you and so on
that's all bound with this world
um so
so helping them it's not on the level of
indulging them emotionally
or my mother will be upset if i'm not
here i must be here then and forsake
everything else that's important for the
practice no that's you're not helping anyone
no that's you're not helping anyone
but if you're there to establish it in
virtue and that's it that's the extent
yeah even if she's unhappy with you not
being there even if parents are unhappy
with you leaving and so on
so you want to you want to help them on
that level that actually matters not
just that makes them feel good
so yeah so when you when i first read
that you can't repay them unless you set
them up a stingy parent in generosity
and so on but you you have to start with
yourself you can't of course you become
yourself in that virtue of my parents i
in a way you can teach them by example
yeah that's all really well yeah exactly
so so in that that in that sense you
kind of um accomplish
two goals with one effort
establish yourself in virtue and show
the example that you know to those who
will kind of learn from it because
that's the only path of getting yeah and
also that is a kind of prerequisite for
any successful teaching
like when people you might be teaching people
when people you might be teaching people
and they might make sense of what you're
saying but if they look and see you do
the opposite they will dismiss what you
said naturally
but if they look and see exactly what
you're saying they should do that you're
already doing it and living it then okay
they can't argue with it they can't
dismiss it
um so
so doing it yourself uh establishing
yourself and all of that it is kind of a
prerequisite
to be highly unlikely and unvirtuous
you have even no concept of virtual
behavior and somehow that you would
value establishing your own parents in
virtual behavior when you yourself don't
value it for yourself
and it's all is even more high
even more um
unlikely that you will not uh
that you will be successful
while yourself completed no concept of
virtue ethical conduct established
parents in that through just teaching
them and then they would take it on
while you're doing completely the
opposite um and there's this absolutely no basis
um and there's this absolutely no basis
for any growth there yeah so you would
have to always start with yourself
and that's again that's how to be so how
to be truly grateful
for you to your parents hmm
it's one includes perspective in regard
to um where the value and where the
importance is
and that they can only come out of
gratefulness which can only come out of
your own virtue
so if you're virtuous and practice the
sense of strength in guarding other
senses in the right way like the way of
the training not turned away with the
external duty as you often say
the the framework of gratitude is there
it's the result of it which means the
framework of non-obscuring where the
problem where the issue is for a parent
for others and so on that would be
clearer because as i said yeah if you are not
because as i said yeah if you are not
clear with yourself that's when people
start acting out of uh very emotional
states not out of recognition what's
truly beneficial for parents or for me
or for both you know kusala literally
means beneficial
are unbeneficial
and for that you need perspective
but usually people's perspective is very
limited and beneficial is that which
pleasing and unbeneficial is that which
is displeasing and that's kind of the
criteria of how i feel
so it comes down the same to whether you
know you're engaging with others it's
it's it's always the same criteria
unless you have the other virtue sensory
strain practice properly develop that
perspective of gratitude and so on
of gratitude and so on
uh yeah then you would exactly see so
it's not beneficial to uh indulge in oh
i'll just
make my parents feel good but i won't
make any effort because they always get
upset when i start talking about a
virtue well no see
now you just
enable them in their feelings and you
kind of sacrifice your own perspective
and reason just so they feel good and
you feel good and don't feel bothered
and that's not beneficial for anyone
but yeah if you maybe do that so that
you can then talk about virtue not
preach to them or something like
but try to get the message through
genuinely like to somebody you would
want to help and save even they're
unaware they're dying of this illness
and they could fix it they don't know
how they don't even know that they're
ill so
so
yeah it's going to be some hassle and
work and unpleasantness getting you know
that message across
but if you succeeded yeah you repaid
them for events to come because they
were now virtues because they actually
understood the point of it
they're ethical because they understood
the point of it and that's it you're
done even if they suffer an account of your
even if they suffer an account of your
absence for the rest of their life is
nothing absolutely nothing in comparison
to what you did for them
for the meaning that you are for them
you know that that well yeah yeah the
perspective that they gained through
that that you now stand for basically
sure